Hello world. I'm sure that many of you
watching this video who have been to
Japan before have stepped foot in Kyoto.
The former capital of Japan is one of
the most popular tourist destinations
for both domestic and international
visitors.
And despite the heavy toll that the
COVID pandemic had on tourism, visitor
numbers have boomed here with millions
[music] of international visitors
dropping by Kyoto every year, reaching
the highest levels of visitors in the
city's recorded history.
But this video isn't really about
tourism in Kyoto. It's just an important
piece of the puzzle in figuring out more
about this fascinating city. So, in our
quest to understand what it's like to
live in Kyoto, we interviewed born and
raised Kyotoites, as well as
international residents who now call
Kyoto home. We'll walk through a bit of
the popular Shijo Karasuma area, where a
local will share what her neighborhood
was like back in her childhood days.
We'll also hear about the pros and cons
of living in Kyoto, from the convenient
structure of the city streets to the
high cost of housing. [music] And of
course, we'll share a bit about Kyoto
manners and stereotypes. Are Kyotoites
really that snobby and
passive-aggressive? Or are they like any
of us who take pride in where we come
from? And by the end of the video, we'd
like to hear your thoughts on whether
Kyoto sounds like a city that you'd like
to live in or not. So, without further
ado, let's dive right into life in
Kyoto.
And I'll let Bobby, our producer on the
ground, take it away. Thanks, Greg. One
of the first people we'd like to
introduce is Okumura-san. She's a born
and raised Kyotoite from the Shijo
Karasuma area, a district known for its
trendy shopping and central location.
Shijo Karasuma mall
I might as well go.
And then
none of the day.
>> If I'm being honest, what Okumura-san
says here about cars blocking the
streets feels relevant even now. I'm
sure the streets are much less congested
than what they used to be, but I am
always wary of cars in Kyoto, and they
can be a bit anxiety-inducing.
Anyway,
>> [music]
>> the first stop Okumura-san showed us on
our neighborhood walking tour was the
Shin-Pukan, a shopping center and hotel
that was recently built around the
former Kyoto Central Telephone Office. I
say around because the facade of the
historical landmark was kept intact,
even though most of the structure was
replaced. The Shin-Pukan is filled with
trendy shops and gets quite a bit of
foot traffic. It is one of many examples
in Kyoto City of old buildings being
repurposed or updated [music] to keep up
with modern interests.
Like the Manga Museum. What was once a
public elementary school has become a
hip museum complex with cafes, shops,
[music] and a popular green space for
people to lounge in.
Unfortunately, it wasn't open when we
were filming, but it's a neat spot to
check out if you're looking to relax a
bit. [music]
And something neat was that Okumura-san
happened to have a photo of herself
participating at a Heian period parade
back in the '90s, where participants
gathered at this very elementary school.
Anyway, let's get back to Okumura-san,
who will quickly guide us Nishiki
Market.
>> [laughter]
>> Once we made it out of Nishiki Market
unscathed, we headed over to the
financial district of Karasuma Dori,
where you'll see some of Japan's most
prominent banks on full display.
While the architecture here is quite
modern, you can still see some Showa era
influences on the outside of the
buildings.
This out with the old and in with the
new, while keeping a bit of the old
intact, [music] seems like a frequent
theme in Kyoto city.
For those of you who are unfamiliar with
Gion Matsuri, it is one of the largest
and most famous festivals in Japan,
dating back to the 8th century. It's an
annual celebration that lasts the entire
month of July with various events and
parades happening every day.
And in such parades, there are these
large ornate floats called Yamaboko
floats hauled around by neighborhood
volunteers.
All 33 of these Yamaboko floats are
stored in the specific zone of Shijo
Karasuma, and so this neighborhood is
appropriately called Yamabokocho.
And in this area that is steeped so
richly in culture and tradition, is
where you'll find weaboo central, that
is, the Pokémon Center.
>> [laughter]
>> During the rest of our walk, we passed
by other local landmarks that
Okumura-san grew up with, like the YMCA,
where she learned how to swim. Or the
former Shimin Kaikan, where the Pokémon
Center now stands. Okumura-san played
table tennis with friends after school.
And we even grabbed a refreshing coffee
at the snazzy kissaten chain called
Inoda Coffee, which, according to
Okumura-san, any true Kyotoy is bound to
know.
So, now that we familiarized ourselves
with a bit of downtown Kyoto, let's hear
from some of our other Kyotoy friends
that we interviewed about what they like
and don't like about life there.
And to give you a bit of context about
their backgrounds and experience in
Japan, I'll do some brief introductions,
starting with my friend Arisa. She's a
popular content creator in Kyoto who
promotes various towns and regions
throughout Japan.
She married a Kyotoy, and they are now
raising a young daughter. Akari is a
born and raised Kyotoy who's currently
living in Tokyo for career purposes, but
plans on moving back to Kyoto in the
future. Her family has run a gold leaf
business for multiple generations and so
they are probably as traditional as it
gets when it comes to Kyoto. Clementine
is a French fashion designer who has
lived in various parts of Japan
including downtown Kyoto, Osaka,
Miyazaki and now the quieter western
part of Kyoto city. She and her husband
will have lived in Japan for over 10
years now and are raising their son in
Kyoto.
Aran is a photographer and translator
who has lived in several cities
throughout Japan including Nagoya, Osaka
and Okayama who now calls Kyoto home.
Yuki was born in Kyoto and raised near
Matsuo which is relatively close to
Arashiyama. He and his wife Mai both
have family in Kyoto and are currently
raising a baby boy.
And these lovely women are the crew of
Atelier Iro, a salon in downtown Kyoto
that offers traditional Japanese
hairdressing and antique kimono wearing
experiences for both tourists and
couples taking wedding photos like we
did.
So now that you're acquainted, let's
hear what they have to say. Hi, my name
is Arisa. I'm from Malaysia and I've
been living in Kyoto for probably
probably around 8 years already.
I love it. To be honest, as much as I
have complaints, but don't we all? And
yeah, I I can't imagine a better place
to live than Kyoto. To put it in words,
I guess it's to say that the slow pace
of life because in bigger cities we're
constantly rushing, you know, trying to
get to one place to another. But in
Kyoto, we have a good balance of both,
you know? There are times where you need
to rush like when you're in the in the
Kyoto station, you feel that. And the
minute you step out of it just two stops
like in Shijo area like where we are
right now, you feel like the slow pace
of life, you know? You take a step back,
enjoy
just the view
and just little things like even
walking, you just discover something new
every day. It's like, "Oh, I've never
noticed that before." even though I
walked this path like 100 times.
Kyoto and Nippon machi na
>> [laughter]
>> I love
just visiting like local tofu ya san or
yuba shop that that's like really old
and you get to talk with like grandma
and grandpa.
Visiting all the traditional traditional
but modern store. I feel like if it's
only traditional it's hard like the
offering is very traditional but and
like some businesses like innovated
themselves and make like and
not that modern offerings. So, I like to
take all my friends to those places.
So, like you get to feel the core, but
at the same time it's quite modern.
When I want to go out to drink with
friends, like this is definitely a place
to do that. And if I want to just like
shut and like chill,
I could do that. Like I could be here by
myself and still have fun. And there are
plenty of opportunities to meet people.
Yeah, it's it's like lives up to its
expectations. Like
literally like if you're like in
Kawaramachi area
and like you think it's too noisy and
there's too many people around, you go
walk like a block and end up in
a quiet place and
yeah, you can end up like in a quiet
place that's like close to nature.
And I think I like that duality of
Kyoto. You can't get that in Tokyo. And
I don't think you can get you can get
that in Osaka, either.
So, yeah. Kyoto is still very special to
me and I plan on being here for a while.
>> [laughter]
>> It's annoying changing and it's good but
still like especially older generation
are very conservative and they don't
want to change anything. Especially my
dad with my family business they really
like
he doesn't want to do anything and it's
not like
it's not like you're trying
nothing. Yeah.
So some people are a bit like that.
conservative and
Yeah, so that's Yeah, that's probably
the one thing that I don't like about
Kyoto.
I definitely had an easier time making
friends with other foreigners out here.
Um
and
my experience in other places in Japan
liv- other places I lived in Japan is
like I could talk to a stranger a
strange a Japanese person that's a
stranger and like they'd be a little bit
receptive to it but
I think you kind of just get grouped in
with the tourists if you're a foreigner
here.
Um
and I could kind of sense the tension
there. Um I used to work
with a team of I think maybe I told you
before but a team of Japanese people and
they weren't all from Kyoto.
And they said they really felt excluded.
Like they really felt like foreigners
for to the other people who are
born in Kyoto.
Or the fact that people are very nice.
I'm speaking about Kyoto.
But then
they don't have a choice. That's how
they interact. You have to be nice
in a way.
There's a special way about Kyoto, I
think, of being like this. Like Osaka
doesn't have this.
And when I was in the US, I could
definitely not. Like people speak to you
because they want to. If they don't want
to, they they don't. Or if if they're in
a good mood, they'll show they're in a
good mood. If they're not, then they
they're not going to engage with you.
But here, I think there's this pressure
of always being
nice and polite.
And sometimes I tell Will like, "Oh,
this lady was really nice."
And like I speak up about it afterwards,
and he's like, "Yeah, but
she's Kyoto, you know."
And I was like, "Oh, yeah, okay, of
course. Yes." So, it it's not deeper
There's nothing deeper than this. She
was just nice.
It It doesn't mean that she appreciated
us. That's what I mean.
And this I find
a bit hard because once you know it, you
start to analyze.
But also, I don't want to analyze.
Like I I would rather stay naive and
think, "Oh, maybe she likes me or a
little."
And also, not everyone is like this.
Like whatever rule
exists or habits, not everyone is
actually following the rules. So,
sometimes people are just genuinely
nice.
As Akari, Clementine, and Aaron
mentioned, Kyotoites have a reputation
for being a bit on the conservative and
exclusive side. So, I wanted to dive in
a bit more and hear from everyone about
the stereotypes associated with
Kyotoites.
You can't I can't generalize all of
Kyoto people, but
in the city central, where um where
we're currently at, Kyoto City, they
have what we call Kyoto pride. I mean,
definitely so, because they were the
capital city. You know, after the Nara
move, and then they were for longest.
And they still carry this pride till
this day, even though it's been like
centuries already.
So, yeah. For other areas, if we're
talking about like Fushimi, um
Arashiyama, or even Miyazu, like up in
north east side,
they probably won't have this They're
likely more friendlier and less colder
when we talk.
Yeah.
And we don't have what we You know, like
everyone assumes Kyoto people have this
passive-aggressive notion when they
speak. Like it is time to go back. They
ask you, "Do you want o-chazuke?"
Kind of thing. I mean, it's I know it's
a joke, but not a very healthy joke, you
know? We're not all Kyoto people are
like that.
Cuz my family doesn't do that.
You know, people think Kyoto people are
like mean and exclusive.
And it's kind of true when I look at my
grandma and grandpa's generations. Yeah,
I grew up in like pretty much the center
of Kyoto. So, I my attitude is
definitely like Kyoto-jin, but
personally, I feel more like
open.
Hopefully, I'm more open than
like my grandparents' generation. Kind
of. And I feel a lot of young Kyoto
people are quite like open and like
you know,
boken-teki, like adventurous, and
yeah, doing edgy stuff. So, I think the
culture itself is changing.
But, yeah. I think we're still
Kyoto-jin.
But, the definition of Kyoto-jin is
hopefully changing to be better.
I think that people outside of Kyoto
don't look forward to meeting Kyotoites
because they have like a
sense of superiority.
And I think that's
true, but it depends on the demographic.
If you're like
born in the Showa area,
from my experience, like the people,
yeah, old people that I meet like at
work and stuff like that, they kind of
have that like superiority complex. But
I feel like that has completely gone
away in people from the younger
generation that I've met. They don't
really, yeah, I don't know. They don't
look down on people from other
prefectures and when they go to when
they go to other prefectures like they
fit right in. Like they're not like
automatons at all.
So I feel like whatever
people didn't like about it
does not exist in our current
generation, I'd say. Yeah.
Yeah, it's not pride. Like they still
have pride in like they still love being
from Kyoto, but like it's never
something that keeps them from making
relations with other people.
To piggyback on Yuki's example of
passive-aggressive Kyotoite behavior, we
decided to do some middle school drama
club level reenactments for you.
>> [music]
[music]
>> So in this situation, Yoko on the left
is now complimenting her friend's child.
She's saying in a polite way that
they're playing too loudly and perhaps
too often. But to someone who doesn't
read between the lines or the air the
situation, such comments can be
misinterpreted as positive in meaning.
Here, Yoko points out my watch so that I
will inadvertently look at the time and
decide for myself that it's getting too
late and that I should get going. But if
you're on the innocent side, you might
just think that it's a conversation
starter or that they're just being
friendly, dashing the Kyotoite's hopes
of you leaving sooner rather than later.
These were just shot for fun and I'm not
sure how common such interactions are
these days, but it might be helpful to
keep in mind that in Japan, and perhaps
especially in Kyoto, direct statements
and confrontations can be quite
uncomfortable. So, using roundabout
language and gestures is a sort of
culturally convenient way to get the
point across while avoiding accusations
of being rude or aggressive.
I think it's mostly because the Kyoto is
a smaller city. So, it feels that in
Kyoto, it feels like everybody's
watching you and especially with family
business and everything. Because all my
Not all, but a lot of my friends grew up
with the family business and there are
lots of like old businesses in the
neighborhood. It feels like you are seen
as the family business's daughter. So,
it feels a bit like restricted. Like um
Like when I do something weird or silly,
like it's so bad. Like I don't want to
damage the repu- Not like reputation,
but like it's going to spread out in the
neighborhood so fast anyways, so it's a
bit like
So, that's That All this pressure makes
everybody behave really well in front of
each other. At the same time, they talk
behind everybody's back at the as well.
So, it's that that's what makes Kyoto
people like
look mean. Like and I thought about it
and maybe it's because of the family
businesses Kyoto because it's really old
and you can't like damage your ancestors
like
like what they built up and everything.
So, you have to behave really well.
Perhaps the biggest elephant in the room
is the topic of tourism in Kyoto. Are
there too many tourists in Kyoto? Does
Kyoto even need tourism that much? Are
the problems that we hear online about
tourism simply exaggerated? I wanted to
hear from the people we interviewed
their thoughts on the matter. So, first
let's follow my friend Clementine
through a bit of Arashiyama's famous
bamboo garden, one of the most popular
tourist spots in Kyoto.
Sometimes it is peaceful. Like
like there's no reason why there's
nobody, but sometimes you just arrive at
the right time and it's still quiet. Do
you find these types of places still to
be quite like inspiring or
Yes, like right now where you were
walking and I just saw the camellia
in bloom and the birds
sound of birds even if there was
a crowd, I think if I had time to
appreciate it or I would.
But it's hard. It's hard when you're
trying to make your way between people.
The place still looks pretty good, but
the
I don't know.
The subtleties are gone. Yeah, and you
have you have to think about other
people because you hear them. Whereas if
you walk and it's quiet, you can get
lost in your thoughts or Yeah. Yeah.
Do you want to go a bit more?
Cuz that's I think a question that
people ask me often, like is it worth
going? But it's hard to say yes or no
because it depends why you're why you're
going. What are you looking for? If you
want to see
then go. If you want to
relax in the nature, you can choose any
other bamboo forest
in Japan and there's like thousands of
them, too.
From my personal feelings, I don't feel
like there's more people. I know
everyone says there are more people, but
I've always been to places that were
really, really crowded.
So, now I notice them more because I
live in Japan for longer
and I notice especially um
on a fashion point of view, like how
people dress. No. Sometimes you see
ladies in the
you say like uh
workout outfits.
Like very uh shave showing exactly
um leggings and things. And if I was
living in France still, I think I
wouldn't be surprised, but here it's so
rare to see that when you see it, it
attracts your attention.
Oh, so it's quite funny because I think,
"Oh, they don't live in Japan."
Whereas sometimes you can see foreigners
how they behave or how they dress,
it can give you a hint that they live
here.
I feel like
the area that's got crazy is very
limited. It's only around the Kiyomizu
Temple, like
Mhm. Yeah, Gion area. So,
actually, I don't think any of our like
daily life were affected that much. Uh
uh yes, yeah. I don't know, except for
like buses and trains. Now, my mom's a
bit annoyed with the buses. Like, she
can't catch a train the buses. Like they
don't know. But they are like
putting more buses in like the city. So,
it's it's not too bad. I feel like some
um tourists are actually looking for a
quick, easy-to-digest kind of
experience. Like, some people just want
to take photos for Instagram and like
just go to Kiyomizu-dera and wear
kimono, and that's good.
But I I wish more people could
appreciate like deeper culture, toka.
And like, if the market wants something
more authentic, then more of those
authentic businesses can thrive and and
more people would make those businesses.
I know it's hard to like communicate the
like deeper
um culture, and that's why people like
do get quick and easy experiences. But I
hope we can make it like easier to
digest. And So that more people can like
appreciate or like enjoy the real
culture. I I just want to say there's a
lot to a lot more to see.
Not just in Kiyomizu-dera or Kinkaku-ji.
I hope more people actually come to like
local areas or just enjoy Kamogawa like
chilling in Kamogawa.
So that
so that they can feel the local people's
lives.
Okay, we know we have like an an inbound
issue in I mean, it's usually only like
segregated to certain spots of Kyoto.
Well, with better management, I'm pretty
sure we can disperse those, you know,
like what other prefectures are doing.
Because other prefectures don't have
this issue.
They are more welcoming towards
tourism
cuz they need it to survive.
In Kyoto, we cannot say that oh, we have
too much. We don't need it. No, you do
need it because we have seen the effects
of COVID. For 3 years when
when the world was when Japan was shut
off from the world, a lot of businesses
were affected.
Um as a local who has been here, I've
seen
I've seen lots of shops come and go
during the 3 years alone.
So, it's crucial for the economy.
But we need to do better to have a
better infrastructure to accommodate
that.
>> [laughter]
[laughter]
>> I wanted to include some information we
came across about overnight visitors in
Kyoto from the year 2024. This is a
particular year because it was the first
time in the city's history when inbound
tourists outnumbered domestic tourists
with 8.21 million foreign visitors
versus [music] 8.09 million Japanese who
stayed overnight. Another metric that
caught our attention was from the
Ministry of Land, Infrastructure,
Transport, and Tourism. The survey data
shows what percentage of Japanese and
inbound visitors plan on going to
specific spots in Kyoto City. It's not
too surprising to see that for inbound
tourists, Kiyomizu-dera hits the number
one spot at 66.6%
followed by Nijo, the Gion area, Fushimi
Inari, and the usual suspects.
But what surprised me was that the
number one spot for Japanese visitors is
not Arashiyama or Kawaramachi or any
obvious tourist spots, but the Kyoto
Station area. This could be because the
term visitor is quite vague. A lot of
visitors come to Kyoto from nearby
cities like Osaka, Nagoya, and Kobe for
day trips.
So perhaps there are a lot of visitors
who simply want to shop around Kyoto
Station and soak in the vibes before
going back home.
>> [music]
>> But here's another stat for you to mull
over. Over 50 million visitors come to
Kyoto every year, and roughly 80% of
them are Japanese. So, by simply looking
at the numbers, we can comfortably say
that there are more Japanese people who
visit Kyoto than inbound tourists.
>> [music]
>> On a side note, looking at these numbers
might be helpful for tailoring your
itinerary in Kyoto. If you want to avoid
large crowds, just avoid the places with
the highest percentages.
>> [music]
>> Anyway, I thought it was important to
include some stats in here so that we
have a balance of anecdotal and
statistical evidence.
>> [laughter]
[laughter]
>> I hope that
images of
visitors doing something stupid
don't
take over
in the media so people have a general
bad idea about foreigners in general and
get mixed up with between some very few
rude visitors
and all the rest of us who live here.
But like the other day or this last
fall, there were a couple of girls
um sitting on my neighbor's rock in
front of the house, and then I was
really debating inside myself cuz I was
with a customer
uh who came for a full day sewing, so we
take a lunch break together at the end
of the street. And we came out and I saw
these two girls and I was like, oh, I
know my neighbor wouldn't like people
sitting on this rock.
And I didn't know if they could speak
English
because I couldn't tell where they were
from. And and I felt that like I had a
really big debate within myself in a
just in a fractions of seconds like,
should I tell them to move?
Uh, also they're not being loud, they're
not trashing.
Should I
should I say something or is it my place
to say something? Are they going to be
confused if I say something?
Well, I didn't say anything. But I think
if it would have been something worse, I
would have say something.
Uh, sometimes I find trash
in front of my house here where I work.
Um, and I think if I saw the person who
did this, I would
certainly say something because there's
a bin just around the corner. But this
this being foreigner or Japanese, it
doesn't matter. I don't want people to
put their waste on the on the ground.
Now, onto the topic of raising a family
or starting a life in Kyoto.
Many of the people I interviewed either
have kids or have raised kids in Kyoto.
So, I want to hear what they had to say.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay,
I don't know anything about
Kyoto.
I don't
know
anything about Kyoto.
>> [laughter]
>> The last thing I wanted to touch on was
the pleasing aesthetic of Kyoto city. As
Greg explained in a previous video about
Kyoto's strict architectural rules, city
planners and locals have made a
concerted effort over the years to
maintain Kyoto's beautiful and
interconnected visual identity. And so
it was fun to hear from my friends about
their feelings on the vibe and look of
Kyoto.
>> [music]
>> You know, if you pass the house,
especially in the city center,
here we have little gardens and things,
but in the city there's no gardens.
There is not that much space between
your door entrance and the road, but
still people are going to put a lot of
plants in pots.
And sometimes they're going to pile up
in front of the house to the point that
it looks
almost too much, but in a nice way.
That's really an image of Kyoto for me.
Um another image,
wood and brown.
And Kyoto is very brown and earth color.
Kissaten, which is something I
discovered in Kyoto. So, I know it's not
only in Kyoto, but that's for me there
are some really nice ones in Kyoto.
The architecture and just like the
presence of culture here does contribute
to the positive experience that I have.
I'm pretty used to the classical
architecture here, but I recently had an
experience where I took a night bus
from Tokyo to Kyoto and I arrived like
at 4:45 or like 5:00 a.m. or something
like that. So, none of the buses or
trains were running.
And I had like a 3-km walk with my
luggage. But yeah, I started walking and
then I put on my headphones and I was
listening to Nujabes and yeah, I like
walked past like Hongan-ji Temple and a
lot of like routes that I usually a lot
of streets that I usually don't take.
And there's a lot of beautiful
architecture there that I don't really
get a chance to enjoy. And what made it
even better is like it's 5:00 a.m.
Nobody's around.
If you could take a couple of more
pictures to put together, that would be
great.
Kyoto to make more to eat.
a smoothie
Nihon Nihonjin
I can't do that.
I feel I'm lucky that I grew up in
Kyoto. It's very like specific and and
also hopefully I want to go back to
Kyoto in a few years and do more of the
businesses that I wanted to do like the
deeper culturally embedded but I want to
offer like those to everybody traveling
as well and be open.
And on that note, we wrap things up with
a big thanks to everyone who helped out
in this video. We've left links to their
shops and social media links in the
description.
Thanks for watching. [music]
See you next time. Peace.
What's it like living in a big tourism
city where you're from?